-= LUO MADE DVD =-
1757年
在美洲殖民地上
英法兩國爭奪殖民領土
征戰進入了第三年
一支僅存三人的印地安部族
他們在哈德遜河以西.....
邊陲一帶狩獵
丹尼爾戴路易斯
梅德琳史托
-= 大地英豪 =-
最後的摩根戰士
喬迪梅
羅索米耳斯
衛斯史杜迪
編劇:麥可麥恩、克利夫考耳
製片:麥可麥恩、杭特羅耳
導影:麥可麥恩
兄弟，我們很抱歉殺死你。
對於你的勇氣、速度和耐力，我們深感敬佩
你好!
Hello!
約翰 柯麥隆!
John Cameron !
金卡加，你好嗎
Chingachgook!
How are you?
"生命之神"很眷顧我，約翰
The Master of Life is good, John.
又過了一年了..
Another year passed.
你好嗎
How is it with you?
還過得去，我很好
Getting along. Yes, l am.
娜珊約
Nathaniel.
約翰，你又開墾了一塊地
Hello, John.
Cleared another quarter, l see.
是阿...
Yes, l did.
亞力山卓     歡迎
Alexandra.
Welcome.
嘿 傑克，你好嗎?  你好
Jack, how are you?
娜珊約，你好嗎?
Hello, Nathaniel.
很好，謝謝
How've you been?
Good. Thank you.
你們都到哪去打獵了?
Where you boys been trapping?
卡雅赫河的西邊
West of the Cuyahoga.
安卡斯為何跟你們一起?
Why is Uncas with you?
他該找個女人建立個家了
He should have settled with a woman,
started a family by now.
安卡斯你看
Hey! Hey!
Hey, Uncas, look!
我們獵遍摩和克草原沿河五里地
Mohawk field we saw was five mile long
on the river.
與別倫特酋長草原的交界
Chief Joseph Brandt's field.
你們獵了不少吧
You take much fur?
是的  確實不少
That we did.
Lots.
在哈里根區設陷阱
The Horicon's
near trapped-out now.
你們在哪交換毛皮 卡斯特頓？
Where are you
trading your skins?
Castleton?
不是 在史庫伊勒
No.
Schuylerville.
蘇拉維屯墾區
跟荷蘭人交換銀器
Schuylerville,with the Dutch,
for silver.
英國人和法國人會用槍和白蘭地
還有貝珠錢來交換銀器
French and English want to pay with
wampum and brandy.
傑克，你呢?什麼風把你吹來的
So what is it, Jack?
What brings you here?
法國軍隊帶著一群印地安人
離開了卡利城
French and lndian army are heading south
out of Fort Carillon to war against the British.
準備要攻打英國人
我是來幫英國組織民兵的
l'm helping to raise New York's militia to
fill the Crown's levy.
這裡的人會參戰嗎
And the people here are gonna
join in that fight?
明天就知道了   你有啥打算呢？
We'll see in the morning.
Where're you boys heading?
在秋天我們要狩獵
然後再到肯德基過冬
We'll trap over the fall.
Winter in Can-tuck-ee.
找個會說德拉瓦語的女人給安卡斯
Find a Delaware-speaking
woman for Uncas.
她會說，就是你!
然後幫她生許多小孩
She will say,
"You are the one!"
Bear him many children.
生像我一樣的小孩
BOY: Then you can
have a boy like me.
才不要，你太強壯了
Never.
You're too strong.
這樣我會老得快
Turn me old too fast.
這正是他對他媽媽做的事情
That's what he's
doing to his mama.
約翰柯麥隆，謝謝你的招待
MAN: John Cameron,
thank you for
your hospitality.
摩和克族人跟法國人之間並無仇怨
Mohawk traded furs
with les francais.
而且有跟他們交易毛皮
We got no quarrel with les francais.
現在法國人把休倫族、沃太華族
比那基族帶來我們摩和克族的土地上
Now les francais
bring Huron, Ottawa,
Abenaki onto Mohawk land.
現在摩和克族人
要和法國人、休倫等族作戰
Now Mohawk will
fight les francais
and Huron.
我代表摩和克族等共六族人請求說明
l speak for
the Twin Rivers Mohawk
of the Six Nations.
英王二世喬治陛下
非常感謝你們的支持
His Majesty, King George ll,
is very grateful
for your support.
他們還離村莊有多遠?
How far up the valley?
現在他們在威廉城附近
Up to Fort William Henry.
有兩天路程
That's two nights
and a bit from here.
那足以說明他們是我們的敵人!
Should be enough
to remind you all that
France is our enemy.
法軍是你的敵人吧..
France is your enemy.
你說什麼
What did you say?
如果我們走了
他們來攻擊我們的家園怎麼辦
While we're at your fort,
what if the French
attack our homes?
你說阿中尉
What then, Lieutenant?
這就是為了你們的家園、國家、皇上
For your homes,
for King, for country!
所以你們要加入戰鬥!!
That's why you men
ought to join this fight!
為了你們自己的頭皮
愛怎麼做是你們的事
You do what you want
with your own scalp.
但別支使我們怎麼做
Do not be telling us
what we ought
to do with ours.
你這叫愛國嗎
是效忠皇室的臣民嗎?!
You call yourself a patriot?
A loyal subject to the Crown?
我根本不承認我是英國人
l do not call myself
subject to much at all.
我同意一些娜珊約和約翰的話
l agree with some of what
Nathaniel and John say,
但英國仍然統治著我們
but l believe England's
still our sovereign.
我去
l'll go.
我也去對抗法國
We will go to
fight the French.
我們兄弟志願參戰
My brother and l will volunteer up.
傑克 我願和你一起作戰
l'll fight with you, Jack.
我要留在我的農莊上
l'm staying on my farm.
離開參戰的人，
歡迎他家屬來同住，
Any man who goes,
his family's welcome
直到戰爭結束
to fort up with us
till he comes back.
我的意見是
Boys, my sense of it is
我們有足夠的人手組織民兵應召
we have enough here
to fill the county levy,
我們應該參戰
and it's a fight
we ought to make.
但首先要跟韋伯將軍談好條件
But first
we got to get terms
from General Webb.
去哪跟他談呢？
Where are you
meeting him?
我們去亞班尼
We'll go to Albany.
立正!
Attention !
我告訴他們  沒有命令他們
We speak for the men,
not command them.
如果不能隨時離開戰場 回去保衛他們的家園
lf they're not allowed
leave to defend
their farms and families
在法軍攻擊他們時
if the French
attack the settlements,
那就不會有民兵加入作戰
then no colonial militia is going to
Fort William Henry.
你們沒有資格與英國軍隊談條件
They will report or be pressed
into service.
任何被挑中的男性
Any of the boys worth having
若敢違抗徵召，躲入森林者，
can disappear into the forest.
They will be found.
那會怎樣的下場呢？
And where does that leave you then?
他們將會被逮捕
Those men will be
found, arrested. . .
以陛下的仁慈怎麼可能有任何理由
l cannot imagine His Majesty,
in his benevolence,
去反對他在美洲的子民隨時回家
would ever object to his loyal
American subjects
去保衛他們的田園、女人和孩子
defending their hearth and home,
their women and children
這意思是說 可以讓他們隨時離開
Does that mean they
will be granted leave
能回去保衛家園是嗎?
to defend their homes if the settlements
are attacked?
當然..
Of course.
那麼您已經擁有這支民兵部隊了 將軍
You got yourself a colonial militia, General.
那就是我們樂見的
lt is what we wanted.
少校鄧肯海華報到
Major Duncan Heyward reporting, sir,
我來接受派遣 路上安全嗎?
en route to Fort William Henry
and bearing dispatches. Safe journey,
l trust?
是的，安全
路上遭遇的事
Yes, and l didn't experience anything
比不上這裡的事如此使我訝異
so surprising from Bristol to Albany
as that that l witnessed here today.
什麼事使你訝異?
And what was that?
徵召民兵竟然還要談條件
The Crown negotiating
the terms of service.
我知道，
l know.
但總要有理由讓他們乖乖做事
One has to reason with these colonials
to get them to do anything.
隨然很煩但也只能如此
Tiring, isn't it?
But that's the lay of the land.
我以為大英帝國的政策是....
"世界英國化"，長官
l thought British policy is
"Make the world England," sir.
原來你是被派到威廉亨利堡去
l see you're to serve
with the 35th Regiment of Foot
加入蒙羅將軍麾下的第35步兵團
at Fort William Henry
under Colonel Munro.
我則帶領第60步兵團前往愛德華堡
l'll be marching
the 60th to Fort Edward.
跟少校解釋一下
Explain to the Major,
he has little to fear
他有點擔心那位法國將領
第一，馬奎將軍絲毫不足畏懼
from this General Marquis de Montcalm
in the first place,
所以幾乎用不到民兵助陣
and therefore scant need
of a colonial militia in the second,
第二因為法國人天生就不是打仗的料
because the French
haven't the nature for war.
他們只懂吃喝玩樂
Their Latinate voluptuousness
寧願偷懶作愛直到
火燒屁股了才要打
combines with their Gallic laziness.
And the result is,
他們吃喝成性勝於作戰
they'd rather eat and make love with
their faces than fight.
請問有沒有
蒙羅將軍女兒們的消息
Might l inquire if
General Webb has heard
from Colonel Munro's
daughters?
我正要到亞班尼去與她們會合
然後護送他們到威廉堡去
l was to rendezvous with them
in Albany and escort them
to the fort, sir.
嘿你...蒙羅怎麼叫你的?
You there,
what does Munro
call you?
那蘇格蘭佬派他的盟友....
摩和克族戰士做你的嚮導
The Scotsman has sent you
one of his Mohawk allies
to guide you.
馬瓜
Magua.
蘇格蘭佬的女兒在地主家
The Scotsman's daughters
are at the Poltroon's house.
我派第60團的一個連兵力護送你們
A company of the 60th
will accompany you,
馬瓜會為你們帶路
and Magua will
show you the way.
清晨六點在營地集合
到時見
Dawn. At the encampment,
6:00 a.m. sharp.
See to it you're there.
長官，讓我來
l'll take him
for you, sir.
可娜!
Cora.
鄧肯!
Duncan !
你到這裡多久了?
How long have
you been in Albany?
好多天了
For days and days.
-你呢
And yourself?
剛到
Just arrived.
天阿，見到你真好
By God,
it's good to see you.
我真不知該怎麼跟你說，鄧肯...
l don't know
what to say, Duncan.
我也很希望可以，但我對你的感覺...
l truly wish they did,
but my feelings don't. . .
無法超越友情
Don't go beyond friendship.
你難道看不出來嗎
Don't you see?
尊敬以及友情
Respect and friendship.
不正是婚姻的基石嗎
lsn't that a reasonable basis
for a man and a woman
to be married?
婚後自然會產生感情的
And all else may grow in time?
-是有人這麼說的
Some say that's the way of it.
-是哪些人
Some?
-我表哥尤金、我的父親...
Cousin Eugenie,
my father. . .
-好，可娜.....
Well, then, Cora.
我心裡很清楚如果我兩結合
ln my heart l know,
once we're joined,
一定會是倫敦最美滿的一對
we'll be the most
marvelous couple
in London.
這點我很肯定
l'm certain of that.
何不試著讓你所信賴的人
好比你的父親....
So why not let
those whom you trust,
your father,
來做安排呢?
help settle
what's best for you?
別再猶豫了....
你該試著相信他們的看法
ln view of your indecision,
you should rely
on their judgment.
還有我的
And mine.
你可以再考慮一下嗎?
Will you
consider that?
請再考慮一下好嗎?
Please consider that.
好吧
Yes.
我會再考慮的
Yes, l will.
鄧肯!
ALlCE: Duncan !
哇!你長高羅!
By God, you've grown up.
-我們是明天一早啟程嗎?
We leave in the morning?
-是的
Yes, miss.
我晚上要失眠了，這可是大探險
l shan't sleep tonight.
你有看過紅人嗎?
What an adventure. Have you seen
the red men?
曾看過一些
A few.
我迫不及待要告訴家鄉
的朋友
l absolutely cannot wait to return
to Portman Square,
這些蠻荒的歷險
having been to the wilderness.
我好興奮喔，鄧肯
lt's so exciting, Duncan.
艾麗絲??
Alice?
我們可以休息一下嗎?
ALlCE: Can we rest soon?
當然可以
DUNCAN: Absolutely.
你
You, there.
史考特!
我們必須停下休息，女士們累了
Scout, we must stop soon.
Women are tired.
這裡不行，再往前三里
那裡水乾淨，到那裡休息
Not here. Two leagues.
Better water. We stop there.
不行，就在這片空地休息
No, stop in the glade just ahead.
小姐們休息完再上路，懂嗎?
When the ladies are rested,
we will proceed. Do you understand?
我懂
白人跟狗一樣聽女人的
他們餓的時候  就馬上放下戰斧偷懶吃
你說什麼
Excuse me. What did you say?
馬瓜說.....
我很瞭解英語(英國人)，非常清楚
Magua said,
understand English very well.
部隊不要亂!快
DUNCAN: Hold tight!
Come on !
注意右翼!
Right! To the right!
原地不動，向右方射擊!
部隊!成方正對形!
預備
Prepare your firearms!
As three ranks!
-瞄準，預備
-預備
Make ready!
開火和第二排準備
First and second rank,
present!
開火
Fire!
不!鄧肯!
No, Duncan.
以防你的槍法  高過你的判斷力
ln case your aim's any better
than your judgment.
傷兵得送回去亞班尼，
Your wounded
should try walking
on back to Albany.
北面山路他們沒辦法走
They'll never make a passage north.
住手!我們需要坐騎!
Stop it! Stop it!
We need them to get out!
-他為何把馬放走?
DUNCAN: Why's he
loosing the horses?
-你問他阿!
Why don't you ask him?
很容易被追蹤
幾里外就能聽見馬叫聲
Too easy to track.
They'll be heard for miles.
我們要去威廉軍堡
We were headed to
Fort William Henry.
我們帶你們過去
We'll take you as far as the fort.
我們趕緊離開這裡
We're walking out of here fast.
除非你要等另一支休倫族殺過來
Unless all of you'd rather
wait for the next Huron
war party to come by.
史考特，我想跟你說聲謝謝
Scout, l'd like to
thank you for your help.
威廉軍堡還有多遠
How much further is it?
一天多腳程
Night and a bit.
我們好像已經擺脫他們了
Appears we're well away from them.
也許，但他們不只一夥人
Maybe. Maybe they ain't alone.
-那個休倫人....
That Huron captain back there. . .
-那個嚮導嗎?他是摩和克族人
The guide? He's a Mohawk.
不，他是休倫族人
No Mohawk. He's Huron.
-他為何要殺那女人?
What reason did he have
to murder the girl?
-什麼?
What?
黑髮那個
The dark-haired one.
可娜.蒙羅小姐? 殺她?
Miss Cora Munro? Murder her?
馬瓜從沒見過她，她才到此一個星期
He never set eyes
on her before today.
She's only been here a week.
-有家族仇恨嗎?來報仇的?
Blood vengeance?
A reproach or insult?
-當然沒有!
Of course not!
你們怎麼會在附近
How is it
you were so nearby?
我們發現一隊休倫殖民在跟蹤你們
Came across the war party.
Tracked them.
-你們是要到威廉軍堡報到的是嗎
Then you're assigned
to Fort William Henry?
-不是
No.
那就是到愛德華軍堡了
Fort Edward then?
我們往西到肯塔基
Heading west to Can-tuck-ee.
正在打仗你怎麼往西走
There is a war on.
How is it you are heading west?
我們大致上是往北
Well, we kind of face to the north,
然後在急轉向西
and real sudden-like, turn left.
我以為我們殖民地的殖民
都加入民兵戰鬥了
l thought all our colonial scouts
were in the militia.
現在正在北方打法國人
The militia is fighting
the French in the north !
我不是你們的殖民
我們當然也不會是民兵
l ain't your scout. And we sure ain't
in no damn militia.
一個渥大華族還有兩個法國人
Ottawa, two francais.
你說什麼
What did you say?
鏡子....
Mirrors,
工具.....衣服....
tools,
the clothes.
東西都還在屋裡
Everything
was inside.
-他們什麼也沒拿走
They didn't
take anything.
-他們走得很快
And moving fast.
是一支戰鬥隊伍
And a war party.
我們埋葬他們吧
Let us look after them.
別管他們
Leave them.
儘管他們是陌生人
Whoever they are, though they're strangers,
起碼也該埋葬他們
they're at least entitled
to a Christian burial.
不能讓他們暴屍體此地
They can't be left behind.
-我們走
Let us go, miss.
-我不走  我也見過打仗，
但就沒見過殘殺婦女小孩的戰爭
l will not!l've seen the face
of war before, sir,but l've not seen
war made upon women and children.
而你的冷血同樣這麼殘忍
And almost as cruel
is your indifference.
蒙羅小姐
Miss Munro,
他們並不是"陌生人"
they're not strangers.
我說任他們留在那裡
And they stay as they lay.
你為何不埋葬他們
Why didn't you bury those people?
追蹤我們的人會發現掩埋痕跡
就能知道我們的蹤跡
Anyone looking for our trail
would see it as a sign we passed that way.
你和他們熟識是嗎
You knew them well?
不埋葬他們原來是為了
我們的安全著想....我道歉
You were acting for our benefit,
and l apologize.
我誤會你了
l misunderstood you.
這是意料中事
Well, that's to be expected.
-我父親曾警告過我
My father warned me about. . .
-你父親
Your father?
-金卡加，他要我小心白種女人
Chingachgook.
He warned me about people like you.
-喔是嗎
Oh, he did?
別試著去接近他們
He said, "Do not try to understand them."
也別讓他們瞭解你
Yes. And, "Do not try to make
them understand you.
“那是因為他們是一個品種  分開，毫無意義。”
"That is because they are a breed apart
and make no sense."
他們為什麼會退回去
Why did they turn back?
這裡是印地安墓地
Burial ground.
一個品種  分開，毫無意義
"Breed apart. We make no sense?"
我加註  妳是特例
ln your particular case, miss,
l'd make allowance.
非常感謝
Thank you so much.
你原本的家人呢
Where is your real family?
我的父母、姐妹全被殺害了
They buried my ma and pa
and my sisters.
金卡加從法國獵人手中帶我回來
Chingachgook found me
with two French trappers,
待我如同親生
raised me up as his own.
-我很遺憾
l'm sorry.
-我記不起他們了，不過一、二歲的事
l do not remember.
l wasn't but one or two.
你在哪裡學的英語
How did you learn English?
十歲時我父親送我和安卡斯
到鎮上教會學校學的
My father sent Uncas and l
to Reverend Wheelock's school when l was 10.
為何你的朋友要住在
這偏遠又毫無防衛的地方呢
Why were those people living
in this defenseless place?
他們在七年工期滿後
After seven years
indentured service
就來此維吉尼亞安居了
in Virginia,they headed out here
窮人也只能住得起邊疆
'cause the frontier's
the only land available
to poor people.
在這裡他們沒有負債
Out here,
they're beholden to none.
也不必處處受人管束
Not living by another's leave.
他們姓柯麥隆
The name was Cameron.
約翰亞力山卓柯麥隆
John and Alexandra Cameron.
我父親的族人曾說
當太陽、月亮兩兄弟誕生的時候
My father's people
say that at the birth of the sun,
它們的母親死了
and of his brother,
the moon,their mother died.
於是太陽就把她的遺體給了大地
So the sun gave
to the earth her body,
讓大地生長萬物生命
from which was
to spring all life.
又從他的胸部抽出星星
And he drew forth
from her breast
the stars.
將星星拋上夜空 以紀念她的靈魂
The stars, he threw into the night sky
to remind him of her soul.
所以那些也是紀念柯麥隆家的星星
So there's the Camerons' monument.
我想也是紀念著我的親人
My folks' too,l guess.
你說得對
You are right, Mr. Poe.
對這裡的狀況我們並不瞭解
We do not understand
what is happening here.
跟在倫敦或波士頓
And it's not as l imagined
it would be,
所想像的完全不同
thinking of it in Boston and London.
-抱歉讓你失望了
Sorry to disappoint you.
-不，正好相反
No, on the contrary.
這樣更能沸騰我的血液
lt is more deeply stirring
to my blood
超出我以前的任何想像
than any imagining
could possibly have been.
威堡就在下一個山脊那裡
NATHANlEL:
Top of the next ridge.
The fort's downhill of it.
團裡的弟兄們
會去那裡的湖邊取水
The men of the regiment will fetch
water from the lake,
生火取暖，供應一切所需
build fires, and provide every
comfort and desire.
我迫不及待的想見父親了
l cannot wait to see Papa.
開火
Fire!
準備  瞄準  開火
Prepare! Point! Fire!
開門
Open up.
少校鄧肯海華報到
l'm Major Duncan Heyward.
杰弗里隊長
Captain Jeffrey Beams.
-我是平斯，我以為你活不到此地
Didn't expect you
to make it through.
-我們去見蒙羅
Let's go to Munro.
-兄弟們!好嗎?
Hello, boys!
-娜珊約!
Nathaniel !
在這裡真是受罪
l need to talk
to you, Jack.
-安卡斯!
-我以為你們不參戰
MAN: Uncas!
Thought you and Nathaniel
weren't joining up.
我們是沒有
We didn't.
-爸爸!爸爸!
Papa! Papa!
-愛麗絲、可娜，你們來做什麼?
Alice! Cora!
Why are you here?
我的援軍呢
And where the hell
are my reinforcements?
去請費普斯先生
Get Mr. Phelps.
我叫你們離遠一點
怎麼不聽話呢
Told you to stay away.
Why did you disobey me, girls?
-幾時說的?怎麼說的?
When? How? l. . .
-在我信裡說的阿
My letter.
-沒有信阿
There was none.
-什麼?  -沒有收到信
What?
There was no letter.
-我派了三個信差突圍去找偉柏
l sent three couriers
to Webb.
-其中一個叫做"馬瓜"對吧
DUNCAN: One called
Magua arrived.
-他沒有叫我們別過來
He delivered
no such message.
-偉柏知道我們被包圍嗎
Does Webb not even know
we are besieged?
偉柏不知情
Sir, Webb has no idea.
當然不會派援軍
And he certainly
does not know
to send reinforcements.
-發生了什麼事
What happened to you?
-在往喬治城的途中遇襲了
On the George Road.
Attacked.
我們沒事
We're fine.
-你還好嗎
-還好
Are you all right?
Yes.
-這裡會變成怎麼樣，爸爸
What will happen
here, Papa?
-我們會沒事的
We'll be all right, girl.
這個叫馬瓜的陷害我們中埋伏
死了十八個人
This Magua led us into it.
Eighteen killed.
這幾位帶我們來到這裡
These men came to our aid.
They guided us here.
謝謝你們
你們需要什麼嗎
Thank you.
Do you need anything?
-要幾桶火藥
Help ourselves
to a few horns
from your powder stores.
-還有乾糧
Some food.
承蒙你們這次恩情
lndebted to you.
可娜小姐，你好嗎
PHELPS: Miss Cora,
how are you?
費先生你好
Hello, Mr. Phelps.
-麥肯太太會拿乾淨的衣服給你們換
Mrs. McCann
will get some dry
clothes for you.
-謝謝
CORA: Thank you.
跟你姐姐去吧
Go with your sister, Alice.
沒事的孩子，
lt'll be all right, girl.
去吧，沒事的
lt'll be all right.
可以瞭解一下戰況嗎長官
Might l inquire
after the situation, sir,
我在山脊上看到法軍的工事
given that l've seen
the French engineering
from the ridge above?
情況就是對方的炮口徑大過我們
數量多過我們
The situation is,
his guns are bigger than
mine and he has more of them.
我們只能挨轟
它們的戰壕每天推進30碼
We keep our heads down
while his troops dig
30 yards of trench a day.
等進入兩百碼的的距離時
When those trenches are 200 yards
from the fort and within range,
它們會裝填炸藥轟垮城牆
he'll bring in his 15-inch mortars,
把我們炸得屍骨無存
lob explosive rounds
over our walls and pound us to dust.
它們現在距離大約300碼
如果每天推進30碼
They look to be
300 yards out.
那我們僅剩三天了
-可惡...
lf they're digging 30 yards a day,
you have three days.
Damn. Damn.
有一個人可以突圍去見韋伯
This man here can make a run
straight through to Webb.
三天時間不夠往返亞班尼
Three days is not enough time
to get to Albany and back
with reinforcements.
-不是去亞堡
兩天前韋伯已經開往愛德華堡
Webb's not in Albany.
He marched the 60th to Fort Edward two days ago.
韋伯在愛德華堡
Webb is at Edward?
-是的長官
Yes, sir.
那只有十二里路
That's only
12 miles away.
他的援軍明天就可以到達
He could have
reinforcements here
the day after tomorrow.
你挑選人讓敵軍轉移注意力
You, sir, pick your man.
Major Heyward will provide a diversion.
我現在寫信
l'll draft out a dispatch.
待會把告急信交給你
Captain Beams
will seek you out
and give it to you later.
還有件事，昨天我們經過
邊疆的柯麥隆一家
Something else.
Cameron's cabin.
Frontier cabin.
看見房子被燒燬 全家也被殺死
Came upon it yesterday.
lt was burnt out,everyone murdered.
是法軍盟友渥太華族干的
lt was Ottawa,
allied to the French.
知道了......
Aye.
那又怎樣呢
So?
那是一支戰鬥隊伍
lt was a war party.
表示它們會攻擊整個邊境
That means they're gonna be
attacking up and down
the frontier.
謝謝你，先生
Thank you, sir.
在這裡的磨和克族、屯墾者
都有家眷在邊境
People here,
Mohawks, settlers,
have family out there.
你說夠了先生
That'll be all, sir!
家毀人亡，無一倖免
Things were done.Nobody was spared.
個人生死事小 國家大事重要
Those considerationsare subordinate to
the interests of the Crown.
將家人生死置之度外
A terrible feature of war
here in the Americas,
Major Heyward.
以盡責打敗法國人為優先
Best keep your eye fixed on our duty,
to defeat France.
成與敗全靠這名信差了
That hangs on a courier to Webb.
我用三頭公牛跟你交換一頓宴席
For my children are the children
of the true faith.
明天在營火會議前
我將與你共唱戰歌
My friendship and esteem is boundless.
Tomorrow, l will sing the war song with you
at the great council fire.
馬瓜
你的"英國朋友"們好嗎
Magua, how are things
with your English friends?
我們是一起的，加入我們
一起聽聽他的消息
We're at one.Join us.Hear what Le Subtil
has to tell us.
英國將軍韋伯跟愛德華堡
的60兵團會合了
The English war chief,
Webb, goes to Fort Edward
with 60th Regiment.
他還不知法國主子正在攻打威堡
He does not know that my father's army
attacks Fort William Henry.
你的任務完成了嗎
Magua was successful?
另外兩名信差死在樹林裡
The other two couriers
died in the forest.
現在蒙羅應該知道
他的信並沒有送到韋伯那裡
By now, Munro would know his dispatch
did not get through.He'll send another.
他會再派信差去
-灰頭佬會再  試的
Grey Hair will try.
有四、五個人包括兩個女人進入城堡
Four or five,including two women,
entered the fort.
灰髮佬的女兒曾險些死在我的刀下
The Grey Hair's children
were under Magua's knife.
但被他們溜了....
They escaped.
如果再落在我的刀下
They will be under it again.
馬瓜你為何這麼痛恨灰髮佬
Why do you hate
the Grey Hair, Magua?
灰髮佬死的時候...馬瓜要生吞他的心
When the Grey Hair is dead,
Magua will eat his heart.
在他死前.....
Before he dies,
馬瓜要在他面前殺死他的女兒
Magua will put his children
under the knife,
讓他親眼看著自己絕種
so the Grey Hair will know his seed
is wiped out forever.
我的工兵在今晚能推進壕溝
My engineers are advancing the trench
through the night.
你的機會很快就會來了
You may have your opportunity soon.
-可娜小姐，有位先生找你
-蒙羅小姐
GUARD: Miss Cora.Gentleman looking for you.
Miss Munro. Hello.
我可以拿嗎
May l?
-這藥膏能夠消炎
-謝謝
lt will seep, and then
it's going to draw.
Thank you, miss.
你跟蒙羅小姐卿卿我我夠了嗎
About done holding hands
with Miss Munro?
我們有事要做
We got some work to do.
你在看什麼，先生
What are you looking at, sir?
我在看你，小姐
l'm looking at you, miss.
蒙羅不肯相信柯麥隆家的滅門
Munro refused to
believe what happened.
他不肯聽這件事情
He does not even
want to hear it.
他一定得聽
Well, he's gonna have to.
到西邊的凌型堡集合
Get together by
the west bastion.
一定要把伊恩、沙裡、翁卡、威廉找來
lan, Sharitarish,Ongewasgone and William.
這料子織得很密
Tight weave?
絲料，射程可以增加四十碼
Silk.Another 40 yards.
誰知道不是土匪干的
MUNRO: And how am l
to know it wasn't a raid
by common thieves?
甘家是被戰鬥隊伍襲擊的
是法軍的盟友干的
NATHANlEL: The cabin
was attacked by a war party
fighting with the French.
他們掃蕩了南方邊界
They're sweeping south down the frontier
襲擊農莊還有摩和克的村子
attacking farms
and Mohawk villages.
而摩和克的男人全滯留在此
All the men are stuck here.
你一個人的話不足採信
l need proof more convincing than
this man's opinion,
我也不能因此放走民兵削弱戰力
before l weaken the fort's defenses
by releasing the militia.
金卡加的意見也是相同的
Chingachgook's of the same opinion
about the raid.
他們父子的話語可抵聖經
Taken together,that's gospel.
威堡的成敗要靠援軍
Your fort will stand
or fall depending
on Webb's reinforcements,
而不是靠這一點民兵
not the presence of the colonials.
研判軍情的是我，不是你
l judge military matters here,
not you.
你的判斷權責不能超越
Your judgment is not more important
than their right,
他們保全家人、農莊的權利
under agreement with Webb
to defend their farms and families.
海華少校當時也在那裡
他也有看到
Major Heyward was there.
He was at John Cameron's.
He saw what it was.
你確實看到了什麼?少校
What exactly did you see, Major?
我所相信
l saw nothing that would lead me
我看到的是....
to the conclusion it was other than a raid
一般土匪的搶劫殺人
by savages bent on thievery.
-你撒謊
You're a liar!
少校
Major!
蒙特康是個軍人不是屠夫
Montcalm is a soldier
and a gentleman,not a butcher.
你說得簡單，
Easy for you to suppose.
他們的家人有難  你的沒有
lt's their women and children alone
on the farms, not yours!
-別忘記自己的身份，先生
You forget yourself, sir!
-我們沒忘記韋伯將軍給我們的承諾
We're not forgetting Webb's promise.
英國人當然遵守承諾
民兵要留下是因為.....
British promises are honored,
and the militia
will not be released,
我需要比他口說更可靠的證據
because l need more definite proof
than this man's word !
他是言重如山
Nathaniel's word's been good
on this frontier
早在你們來邊疆之前
a long time before you got here.
會議結束，民兵留下戰鬥
This meeting is over!
The militia stays.
英國法令不管用了是嗎
Does the rule of English law
no longer govern?
法令被專制取代了是嗎
Has it been replaced
by absolutism?
如果英國法律沒辦法信任
lf English law
cannot be trusted,
-也許那些殖民
maybe these people
would do better
應該去跟法國人講和
making their own peace
with the French.
-這是擾亂軍心
That is sedition !
-這是事實
That is the truth !
-我會把你打出去
l'll have you beaten
from this fort.
有一天，我想你和我會產生嚴重的分歧
Someday l think you and l are gonna have
a serious disagreement.
任何人煽動逃兵
Anyone fomenting on
advocating the leaving
of Fort William Henry
都會被絞死
will be hung for sedition.
任何人逃兵捉到一律槍斃
Anyone actually caught leaving will be
shot for desertion.
這是最後決定，出去
My decision is final !
Get out.
可娜
Cora?
我有話跟你說
l wanted to talk to you.
可娜，跟鄧肯談談吧
Talk with Duncan, Cora.
我自己來，不能這麼沒用
l must manage.l cannot be
an invalid schoolgirl.
-愛麗絲
Alice.
-我去看看費先生需不需要幫忙
l'll see if Mr. Phelps
needs anything.
抱歉，我不是有意的
l'm sorry.
l didn't mean to. . .
可娜，等我們遠離此地
Cora, when we come together
back in England
回英國結婚之後
and are married and away from this place,
在此做過什麼都不重要了
what had to be done and said here
will matter not at all.
這點我很肯定
l'm certain of that.
我曾答應要考慮的事情
Duncan, l promised you an answer.
你的堅持和毅力使我受寵若驚
You've complimented me
with your persistence
and patience.
但我決定
But the decision l have come to
我寧願抱憾終生
is that l'd rather make
the gravest of mistakes
也不願違背自己的判斷
than to surrender my own judgment.
請接受這個最後的答案
Please take this
as my final answer.
答案是 "不"
lt must be no.
我明白了
l see.
-娜珊約，你本來就反對組民兵
lAN: Yeah, Nathaniel,
but you weren't ever for being here.
-對，我現在還是不贊成
That's right.l saw it that way then
and l see it that way now.
如果我有親人在屯墾區，
lan, if l had kin
in the settlements,
我早就走了
hell be damn sure
l'd be long gone.
違反軍令怎麼辦
What do we do about
being under Crown law?
我認為如果他們拋開王法
一意孤行的話
l believe if they
set aside their law
as and when they wish,
他們就無權支配我們
their law no longer
has rightful authority
over us.
他們根本是暴政
All they have over us
then is tyranny.
而我不願受暴政壓迫
And l will not live
under that yoke.
所以我不會留下來
So l will stay here no longer.
逃兵被抓要槍斃
Anyone caught
leaving the fort
could be shot,
個人自行決定去留
so each man make
your own decision.
要走的人一小時候此地集合
Those who are going,
be back in an hour.
從北牆的暗門出堡
Out the northern sally port.
走沼澤東側
Strike for the east side
of the swamp
繞過法軍警戒線
till you clear the French picket line.
再往北翻過山脊然後轉西南
Head north over the ridge,
then come about southeast.
到"小草地"之後左轉，
就可以避開法軍前哨站
Fork left in Little Meadow
and you're free of
the outpost and skirmishes.
我們早該離開這裡了
Should've gotten
out of this long ago.
隊長，我們沒家人
所以打算留下幫忙
Got no families, Captain.
Figured we'd stay
and give a hand.
我會在菱形堡掩護你們離開
l'll cover you from
the top of the bastion.
-你不走嗎
You're not coming with us?
我有留下來的理由
l got a reason to stay.
這"理由"是醫療室那個穿裙子的吧
That reason wear a striped skirt and
work in the surgery?
是阿，
lt does.
傑克溫斯洛
陪美女好過陪你這醜男
No offense, but it's
a better-looking reason
than you, Jack Winthrop.
動作要快，
黎明前一定要脫離法軍前哨站
Push hard,
'cause you got to clear
the French outpost by dawn.
祝你好運，傑克
Good luck, Jack.
-翁卡，你要留下嗎
-是的
Ongewasgone,are you staying?
是的，
Yes.
法軍太多了
我們的人實在太少
There's too many French.
要死守的人不多
And so few of us to fight.
我們答應英國主子留守
Not too many to die.But we've given our word
to our English fathers.
你，先生 你別動
You, sir! As you were!
Stand off.
別走過來
把他銬起來
Take him.
他們為什麼抓我的白種兒子
因為我幫傑克他們離開
As you were.
別動
這不是你的戰爭
我愛你和我弟弟
你該馬上離開這地方
他們要對我的白種兒子怎樣
他救了我們，能活命多虧了他
He saved us.We're alive only
because of him.
他鼓勵民兵逃亡
The man encouraged the colonials to desert,
當著我的面在這裡鼓動
in this very room,
and in my presence.
他是擾亂軍心的反叛罪犯，
Sir.
He is guilty of sedition.
他該被絞死，跟大家一樣
He must be tried
and hanged like any other criminal,
不管他曾救過你也是一樣
regardless of what
he did for my children.
但他明知後果依然留下
But he knew the consequences
and he stayed.
這也算是罪犯的行徑嗎
Are those the actions
of a criminal?
鄧肯，說句公道話吧
Duncan, do something.
-他明知煽動罪要處絞刑
He knew the penalty for his actions.
應該勇敢受死而不是托你求情
He ought to pay
without sending you
to beg.
-你明知他沒有托我來
你隱瞞你所看到的
You know he wouldn't send me.
You falsely spoke of what you saw.
他說那農莊的情形是實情
What happened at the farm
was as Nathaniel said.
但比不上英國在威堡的利益
是誰授權給殖民們....
But not with enough certainty
to outweigh British interests
in this fort.
評判英國的政策，
是誰准他們未經許可擅自離營
And who empowered these colonials
to pass judgment on England's policies
in her own possessions,and to come and go
without so much as a "By your leave"?
他們不是倚靠你們而活的
They do not live
their lives by your leave!
是靠他們的雙手開墾蠻荒而生存
They hack it out of the wilderness
with their own two hands,
忍受他自己的孩子生處孤獨
bearing their children
along the way.
是你對他迷戀 所以才幫他辯護
You are defending him because you've become
infatuated with him !
鄧肯，你很難讓人欽佩你
評量你整個人上下
Duncan, you are a man
with a few
admirable qualities.
過去我真是高估你了
But taken as a whole,
l was wrong to have thought
so highly of you.
-可娜
Cora!
可娜
我願盡最大努力不讓你傷心
Cora, l would do anything
l could to keep you from being hurt.
但這個人犯了軍法
But this man is guilty
of sedition
為了正義他罪無可恕!
and subject to military justice
and beyond pardon.
正義?
Justice?
如果那是正義
lf that's justice,
那麼法國越快打敗英國美洲的人民
then the sooner French guns
blow the English army out of America,
就越快有好日子過
the better it will be
for the people here.
你不知道自己在說什麼
You do not know
what you're saying !
Yes, l do.
-我很清楚我在說什麼!
l know exactly
what l'm saying !
如果這叫擾亂軍心
那麼我也有罪
And if it is sedition,
then l am guilty
of sedition too.
他們要吊死你
They're going to hang you.
你有機會為什麼不走
Why didn't you leave
when you had the chance?
因為這裡還有我感興趣的東西
Because what l'm interested in
is right here.
我能為你做什麼
What can l do?
不知道韋伯的援軍會不會來
Webb's reinforcements
will arrive or not.
如果沒來此地會被法軍攻陷
lf they do not arrive,
the fort will fall to the French.
如果被攻陷了
你要緊跟著你父親走
lf that happens,
stay close to your father.
緊跟著他
Stay close to him.
法軍不會為難軍官的
The French officers will try
to protect the officers among the English.
不，我要去找你
No. l will find you.
-不要
Do not.
答應我
Promise me.
全世界都在毀滅是不是
The whole world's
on fire.
怎麼樣了
What is it?
記住我的話
Remember what l told you.
緊跟著你父親和軍官
Stay close
to your father and the officers.
蒙羅將軍
我深知您是位英勇的敵手
Colonel Munro,l have known you as
a gallant antagonist.
很高興有機會成為您的的朋友
l am happy to make your acquaintance
as a friend.
悉聽差遣
And l yours,monsieur Le Marquis.
對於貴軍的戰術和頑強的防禦
Please accept my compliments
請接受我的讚揚
for the strong and skillful defense
of your fortress.
若不是由您來指揮的話
Under the command of a lesser man,
這座要塞早已被攻下
it would have fallen long ago,
由於優越的數字和材料
given the superior
numbers and materials.
亦給了我與您抗衡的機會...
Chance has allowed me
to array against you.
馬奎將軍，我是一個軍人
不是外交家
Monsieur Le Marquis,
l am a soldier,
not a diplomat.
冠冕堂皇的話
You called this parley
for a better reason
可以不必多說
than an exchange of compliments.
您已經為了您的皇室付出一切努力
現在為了人道的立場
You have already done
everything which is necessary
for the honor of your prince.
我求您接收我的條件投降
But now l beg you to listen to the
admonishments of humanity.
我求您考慮我提的條件
l beg you to consider my terms
for your surrender.
或許我們也可以繼續作戰
Perhaps the general's
glass can reach
as far as the Hudson
直到韋伯將軍的援軍趕到
and seize the size
and eminence of
the army of Webb?
我的殖民截到
您派出信差的一份文件
My scouts
intercepted this dispatch
intended for you.
在此回覆你的請求
蒙羅將軍
Capitaine de Bougainville.
我並沒有多餘的兵力
可以支援你..
"To Colonel Munro.
Sir, l regret to inform you
而且不可能派得出來
"that l have no men available
to send to your rescue.
建議你提出條件投降
"lt is quite impossible.
這是我的回覆
"l advise you to seek terms
for surrender.
偉柏簽署於愛德華堡
"l remain. Jerome Webb
at Fort Edward."
是韋伯的簽名
This is the signature of Webb.
我瞭解我們弟兄們的個性
寧願戰死也不願意到
And l know
the temper
of our men.
哈德遜灣霍克監獄當戰犯
Rather than spend the war
in a French prison
hulk in Hudson Bay,
they'd fight
to the end.
你聽到答覆了，將軍!
You've had your answer,
monsieur Le Marquis.
我求您
在簽下眾多軍士的死亡命令之前
Sir, l beg you not to sign
the death warrant of so many
至少聽我把話說完
until you have listened
to what l have to say.
繼續
Go on.
您的部隊沒有人會是囚犯
None of your men
will see the inside
of a prison barge.
只要都回到英國去
他們是完全自由的
They are free,
so long as
they return to England
不必留在美國打仗了
and fight no more
on this continent,
民兵也都可以回歸田里家園
and the civilian militia
return to their farms.
武裝呢?
Their arms?
他們仍能全副武裝
They may leave
the fortress fully armed.
我的國旗與制服呢?
My colors?
您可以光榮地帶回英國去
Carry them to England
with pride.
請讓我和同僚商量一下
Allow me to consult with my officers.
我從不預期 活著能看到一些東西
l have lived to see something
which l never expected.
英國官員不敢支持另一個
A British officer
afraid to support another.
韋伯真該下地獄!
Webb can burn in hell.
我們回城裡去跟他們一決死戰
And we'll go back
and dig our graves
behind those ramparts.
死亡和榮譽常被想成是
相同的一件事
Death and honor are thought
to be the same,
但今天我學習到不同的見解
but today l have learned that
sometimes they are not.
長官...
Sir. . .
馬奎將軍
我被您超凡的紳士情操
深深感動
Monsieur Le Marquis,
l am deeply touched
by such unusual
and unexpected
generosity.
城堡交給您
條件是
My fort is yours
under the condition
在黎明前讓我
埋葬弟兄們的遺體
that l be given till dawn
to bury my dead,
以及所有眷屬
準備好長途行軍
to prepare my men and women
for the long journey ahead
並且請您的醫生不吝
醫治我們的傷患
and to hand my wounded
over to your surgeons.
我同意，蒙羅將軍
Granted, monsieur.
英國人和我的法國主子
之間的戰斧已經掩埋了是嗎
ls the hatchet buried
between the English
and my French father?
對   戰士們不再割頭皮了
Yes.
因為白人們已經成為朋友了
Not a warrior has a scalp
and the white men
become friends.
我的主人(法皇)已經擁有這塊土地
My master
owns these lands,
我奉命來驅逐非法殖民
and l have been
ordered to drive off
the English squatters.
英國人已同意離開
They have
consented to go,
他們不再是我的敵人了
so now l call them
enemies no longer.
馬瓜說好要用鮮血染紅戰斧
Magua took the hatchet
to color with blood.
但至今戰斧還是白的
lt's still bright.
除非染上他們的鮮血
才能停止怨恨
Only when it's red,
then it will be buried.
這麼多的日子以來
So many suns have set
since Magua struck the war post.
馬瓜幫著法國攻打英軍
And where is that sun?
何時才能復仇雪恨
我是族人的孩子
Magua is the son of his people
-努力不懈的當上了領袖
-你已然有權利
and he has come
to lead many of them.
帶領休倫族和其他盟族
But Magua has power
with his Huron people
and others here,
我知道
l know well.
馬瓜的村子和屋子
被英國佬燒光了
Magua's village
and lodges were burnt.
馬瓜的孩子 被英國佬殺死了
Magua's children
were killed by the English.
我被抓去給那些為灰髮佬
打仗的摩和克人  作為奴隸
l was taken as slave
by the Mohawk
who fought for the Grey Hair.
馬瓜的妻子以為他死了
Magua's wife
believed he was dead
所以成為了別人的老婆
and became
the wife of another.
而灰髮佬就是原凶
The Grey Hair
was the father
of all that.
當時
ln time,
馬瓜跟摩和克族人稱兄道弟
獲得了自由
Magua became
blood brother to the Mohawk
to become free.
但在他心裡永遠都是休倫族
But always in his heart,
he is Huron.
而他心裡的創傷
And his heart will be whole again
on the day
只能在灰髮佬和他的子嗣
被滅絕了的時候才能痊癒
the Grey Hair and
all his seed are dead.
駐加拿大總司令..你...
會相信英國人的條件嗎?
Does the chief of the Canadas
believe the English will keep the terms?
我擔心我讓他們走了之後
l fear having let them go,
which l must,
我必須再和同一批軍人作戰
.......當我將大軍
開拔往亞班尼的時候
l will only fight the same men again
when l drive towards Albany.
但我不能破壞投降協定
But l cannot break
the term of the surrender
這會使法國蒙羞
and sully
the lilies of France.
先生，城堡是你的了
Monsieur,
the fort is yours.
左三排  準備
MAN: Left three ranks,
make ready!
瞄準
Aim, set.
開火
Fire!
現在  開火
Present, fire!
開火
Fire!
全線射擊
Full company!
灰髮佬! 我要你在死前知道
Grey Hair,
before you die,
我會把刀架在你的子孫前
know that l will put under the knife
your children,
把你的子孫斬盡殺絕
so l will wipe your seed
from the Earth forever.
放開她
Leave her alone!
等你再落入英國人手裡
我會親手吊死你!
When you fall into
British hands again,
l'll have you hanged !
快一些!
Faster!
向那條河流走
Head to the river!
我們要去那裡?    哪裡也不去
DUNCAN: Where are we going?
Nowhere.
我不明白
l don't understand.
待在這裡直到我們離開
This is as far as we go.
如果我們好運
他們會發現我們上岸
lf we're lucky,
they'll figure we beached
我們的獨木舟交錯在地
our canoes and headed cross land.
如果非常好運
他們也會以為我們跌下瀑布
lf we're very lucky,
they'll figure we went over the falls.
唯一的希望是
他們超前我們而去
Our only hope is
that they pass us by.
如果是的話然後呢?
lf they do?
我們就沿著山的南邊走
Take the south rim
down the mountain.
只離愛德華城十二里
lt's 12 miles cross country
to Fort Edward.
如果他們不上當呢?
And if they don't?
你就沒機會享受吊死我的樂趣了
You'll just have to forego
the pleasure of hanging me.
火藥呢?
Powder?
沒了!
Gone.
我的全濕了
Mine's soaking wet!
我們的父親
CORA: Our father. . .
你有看見他嗎?
Did you see my father?
遠遠看見了
From a distance.
不要告訴愛麗絲
Say nothing to Alice.
退後!
Get back!
(GASPS)
是! 去吧
Yes! Go ahead !
這是什麼狗屁計劃?
What the bloody hell
plan is this?
我要你走!
l want you to go!
如果我走，還有一點機會
現在無法還擊
lf we go, there's a chance
there won't be a fight.
因為沒有火藥
There's no powder.lf we don't go in that,
there's no chance.
如果我不走
就完全沒有機會明白嗎?
None! You understand?
懦夫!
Coward !
你必須盡力去做   救你自己
You've done everything you can do.
Save yourself!
如遇厄運
lf the worst happens. . .
你要生存下去
You stay alive!
如果他們沒有殺你
lf they don't kill you,
they'll take you north
up to the Huron lands.
會帶你往北到休倫族的地盤
順從他們，你聽到沒?
你要堅強!你要生存下去!
Submit, do you hear?
You're strong.
You survive!
要活下去! 無論多艱難!
You stay alive,
no matter what occurs!
我都會找到你!
l will find you,
不論多久，不管多遠
no matter
how long it takes,
no matter how far!
我都會找到你!
l will find you.
你們的戰斧紅了．．．
殺了許多英國人，偉大的酋長
馬瓜成了偉大的戰鬥首領
希望得到你的承認
現在我帶來了三個犯人獻給你
馬瓜會將英國軍官賣給法國人
我所得的酬勞都會獻給你
這倆女人是白人指揮官蒙羅的女兒
她們將會被燒死
讓大家共享這份榮耀
我不會說休倫語
你會說法語嗎?少校
l don't speak Huron.
Do you speak French, Major?
是的
Yes.
替我翻譯成法文每一個字都要!
Translate for meinto French
every word as l say it.
我沒有武裝是為和平而來
l come to you unarmed
and in peace
求你聽我陳述事實
to unstuff your ears, Sachem.
請您讓蒙羅將軍的女兒走
Let the children of
the dead Colonel Munro
go free.
不要再加深英國人的仇恨
Take fire out of
the English anger
他們極其痛恨殺害婦幼的人
over the murder of
their helpless ones.
法國主子和我們
比英國人還要強大
我們不怕英國人的怒火
大酋長，法國人製造的和平
被馬瓜破壞了
Sachem, the French fathers
made peace.Magua broke it.
法國人將不再與休倫族做朋友
lt is false that the French
will be friends
still to the Huron.
法國主子會很高興
(SPEAKlNG FRENCH)
不必再擔心和同一支英軍交戰
當白人來的時候
也為我們的命運帶來黑暗
自我還小的時候
族人就常被問到這個問題
休倫族會怎樣做?
現在，連法國人也怕休倫族了
不是更好?
當休倫族在法國人的恐懼中
更顯強大時
我們就可以和他們重新建立協約
我們將會與白人平起平坐
拿亞班奇的土地
奧瑟人的、索克人的狐狸與毛皮
來換取黃金
不會比白人少
會跟白人一樣強大
馬瓜會用這些
英國人和法國人的殖民手段嗎?
Would Magua use the ways
of les francais and the Yengeese?
會嗎?
Would you?
Yes!
休倫族會不會用白蘭地
愚弄阿爾金族的弟兄...
會!
Would the Huron make his Algonquin brothers
foolish with brandy
然後搶奪他的土地
賣給白人換黃金呢?
and steal his lands to sell them for gold
to the white man?
休倫族只想貪婪更多的土地是嗎?
Would Huron have greed for more land
than a man can use?
休倫族會不會愚弄塞內卡族
Would Huron fool Seneca
into taking
搶走所有毛皮
all the furs of all the animals
of the forest
去換取貝珠錢和烈酒呢?
for beads
and strong whiskey?
休倫族人是要殺光敵人的
女人與孩子是嗎?
Those are the ways of the Yengeese
and the francais traders
這些就是英國人和法國人
對付殖民地居民的....
and their masters in Europe infected
with the sickness of greed.
無恥"手段"!
他們歐洲主子早已病態般貪婪
Magua's heart is twisted.
馬瓜的內心已經扭曲
他要學使他扭曲的白人一樣
He would make himself
into what twisted him.
我是"那芬奧達"--"鷹眼"金亞加
l am Nathaniel
of the Yengeese.
是正直的莫希根族收養的白人
Hawkeye, adopted son
of Chingachgook of the Mohican people.
放走這小孩吧
Let the children of the dead Munro
請放走女人和英國軍官吧
and the Yengeese officer
go free.
這是族人給我的榮譽腰帶
This belt,which is a record
of the days
可以證明我的身份和真相
of my father's people,
speaks for my truth.
你在惡毒的離間我們
(SPEAKlNG FRENCH)
馬瓜是個偉大的戰鬥領袖
但他的作法與休倫族不合
(SPEAKlNG HURON)
馬瓜帶走蒙羅的小女兒使他
不致絕種，也藉此平息傷痛
英國軍官回去英軍陣營
以稍減他們的憎恨
蒙羅的黑髮女兒將會被燒死
以償馬瓜殺子之仇
長槍獵人則和平離去
告訴他我跟她交換!我換她!  告訴他!
Tell him l'll trade him.
Me for her! Say it.
燒我! 我是英國軍官! 我跟她換!
我們會去西邊休倫湖
這根本不是智者的決斷!
你們是女人! 奴隸! 狗!
我唾棄你們!
停止!
Stop it!
我是莫希根長槍獵人!
l am La Longue Carabine!
我的死亡是休倫族一大榮耀!
燒我!
My death is a great honor
to the Huron ! Take me!
你有沒有告訴他!?
Did you tell him?
有
Yes.
停止
Stop!
我說是我!
l said to take me.
帶我走!
Take me!
-帶她走!這是賀禮!
-放了他，帶我走!
My compliments, sir.
Take her and get out!
他們要對鄧肯做什麼?
愛麗絲呢?
Duncan. . . What are
they doing to Duncan?
Where's Alice?
愛麗絲!
Alice!
歐卡斯!!
Uncas!
偉大的聖靈和創造生命的主
Great Spirit and maker of all life,
一位戰士就像射向烈日的箭
a warrior goes to
you swift and straight
射向您了
as an arrow shot into the sun.
歡迎他吧，也讓他
做族人營火會議守護神吧
Welcome him,and let him take his place
at the council fire of my people.
他是歐卡斯...
He is Uncas,
我的兒子
my son.
告訴他要有耐心一些
請求死神快些召喚我
Tell him to be patient
and ask death for speed,
族人只差一位就都到齊了
for they are all there but one,
就是我，金卡加....
最後一個莫希根族人
l, Chingachgook,the last of the Mohicans.